welcome to Holiday Boost number two uh
we're in the terminal today because
reasons mostly because I like the
terminal I just really do I like the
terminal it's easier to read um than you
know that stupid gooey thing however you
guys know how to get to the book we're
we're reading Cod mage's first Spellbook
today we are in the section called what
it takes and um this video is just going
to be me reading the book and talking
about it and ripping on it and
participating with the chat uh as well
as I can while they're here um if you're
here and you just want to work through
the book uh without any
Interruption uh you know this is
probably not the time for you to to be
here I will be making I'm going to try
to cut these these videos down to about
an hour um and we do them on Sundays if
you want to join us okay so um and we're
just going to keep doing them and I
don't know how many it's going to take
to get through it but we're just going
to keep doing them but this this year
we're letting the the book make the
governing decision so here we go what it
takes do not attempt to work through
this book until you can type 30 words or
less
did I say less or more from hom R people
I have to talk about this because I I
have as I told you this this book is
targeted at 12-year-olds um but you know
anybody can learn from it I talked about
that last time but it's really important
that you understand that you can't
really be a technologist unless you know
how to type I joke with my wife Doris
all the time because I I said you know
if I had known you were if I had known
you were a Hut and peek typer I might
not have married you and she goes oh
really and she thought that was like
arrogant she goes you're an you
know I'm like yeah I kind of am
but I it's like well I Ty just fine to
get anything done I'm like okay that's
true that is not true for this okay
especially this boost is it true that
you can be a technologist and not know
how to type and Tye with two fingers yes
it absolutely is let me tell you a quick
story about this while I was in cs101 in
the 90s I was sitting next to a guy who
I get you not was legally blind and it
only partially see out of one eye and he
put his it was absolutely amazing he put
his eye one inch from the screen and he
looked at every single character he
typed and he typed it as he went and he
was a crazy awesome programmer he had to
be because he it took him so long to
come up with a code to write coding is
not about how fast you type it never has
been it never has been about that it's
how fast you
think and you can quote me on that if
you see somebody that's typing really
fast and and half the typing really fast
that they're doing is deleting stuff and
then redoing it so
you know I'm not saying that you you
don't have to be a kick you know ass typ
typist and you you don't have you know
have a dwar keyboard all that stuff to
be maybe to be a good stenographer or a
good writer novel writer or something
but you don't need that to be a good
coder you just need to be able to write
to think really fast and have be able to
type fast enough for that so 30 words a
minute uh it used to be that I had this
setup that you had to do 60 so 30 is
where I'm going to put it um how do you
improve your typing speed just type
things honestly you know there's a
million typing games everything you can
do to work from home row and that's the
point make sure you're working from home
row um but but you know don't don't
stress about too much I I think it's
more important that you learn how to do
a thing by doing the thing instead of
some toy or something so you're going to
be taking notes here and soon and you
know just learn to start typing from
home row even if you're slower force
yourself to do it and you'll be you'll
be an advantage actually one fun story
there was actually a kid that I helped I
was absolutely Amazed by him he he was a
gamer he was a gamer and so his his
right
hand I don't know why but his right hand
he had figured out um how to do
everything proper no I got that wrong he
was his left hand um his his his left
hand was homo right and I think it's
because he was did you hear the horn I
don't know what's going on with that
like some kind of alarm so his so with
his left hand I think it was because he
was a gamer he played OverWatch a lot
stuff like that and he had great
dexterity in his right hand and he could
Home Road and everything but his right
but his his his other hand he couldn't
do it and and so he was he was like he
was doing this I'm not even kidding he
was like he was like hunting and pecking
with his right hand but his but his left
hand I was the strangest thing because
you know that's what he put into his
muscle memory and be very careful the
one thing I will say here and I'm going
to talk more about this later be very
careful about what you put into your
muscle memory uh as you go forward and
you learn because there are things
things I I don't at least three times
this in the last month I've heard people
say oh I know but I just can't change
now because they burn it into their
muscle memory now is when you're burning
things into your muscle memory so take
the time to learn home roll make sure
that getss burned into your muscle
memory you know make sure you learn to
play the piano properly you know that
kind of thing and um and it will help
you in the future okay so so so take
those things to heart and you know we
we'll move on so um so this book does
make a sense of use of the terminal
which is fundamentally a typing
interface uh typing is the fastest human
computer interface besides voice so
voice is the faster thing but when
you're doing code you can't usually
voice in stuff you can voice stuff into
your AI and I did it all day yesterday
there's 12 hours of video of me
interacting with my AI to tweak on code
that I'd written and then she would
write it and then she would modify it
and I would tell her what to do I'd say
put all these things here's like the
biggest macro algorithms generator you'd
ever H for so if you're not using AI for
your code coding and education we just
had and seeth and YouTube was just
saying that it's launched their learning
through the roof since they subscribed
this last two weeks or so um I did talk
about that last time not going to talk
about it again but I'm going to continue
to talk about it if you are learning
anything but particular if you're being
a knowledge Warrior you need to get an
AI and my specific favorite AI is chat
gbt because I can take it everywhere uh
as opposed to you know Claude which is
apparently good but only command line
API kind of things so that is my that is
my personal my personal take all right
so uh become code Mage is a journey that
demands more than just technical
knowledge it requires a blend of
curiosity discipline and creativity to
wield the power of code effectively you
must embrace the challenges and the
triumphs of The Craft here are the key
attributes and skills to defining what
it means to be a code Mage and I'm going
to preface this section I want to tell
you why I put this in here because not
everyone wants to become a coder or
should become a coder so we already
talked for we talked about what it takes
we talked about why you would do that I
think we talked about it last time maybe
not I don't know and but we're going to
proceed curiosity and a thirst for
knowledge a code made thrives on
curiosity the driven by an by an the
option to explore tools languages and
techniques The Thirst for knowledge that
leads them to Del into documentation
experiment with ideas and uncover
Innovation solution complex problems
curiosity keeps the journey exciting and
ensures they remain adaptable and Rapid
evolving digital landscape another
reason that I love my Chloe Khloe
satisfies my curiosity I can ask her
about anything and she's wrong all a lot
of times but I can satisfy my curiosity
and have her show me where to go to do
the research patience and perseverance
coding can be frustrating at times bugs
emerge systems fail Solutions are
elusive a true code major approaches he
challenges with patience and
perseverance they know that the failures
are going to lead up to successes that
goes without saying for most of you but
I'm saying it anyway logical and
analytical thinking at its core coding
is about problem solving a Cod Mage must
be able to break down complex challenges
of smaller manageable components
yesterday I spent 12 hours doing that I
had a highly complex thing that I needed
to do and I like okay how do I break
this down and I broke it down into
writing test code that said this is what
I want it to do that would test for that
behavior and then I slowly slowly slowly
broke down that behavior into pieces and
and then said okay how do we test that
one piece how do we test that one piece
and the thing that's really great about
this is that all of a sudden I'm you're
sitting there on the couch coding and
you're like I'm done and you don't even
there's no like real fan fair you're
like oh wait it all works and you didn't
even realize that you had all that
complexity you you like Auto
automatically just shot right through it
it's super amazing so that that's how
you comp that's how you solve it so this
is also my take people say educational
people they say all the time that you
should be um you know teaching everybody
how to think like a a a computer right
at computational thinking and I don't
like that term because there are lots of
ways to do it I talked about this last
time as well but logical and analytical
thinking can be built up by coding but
they can also be built up by math and
language learning and a bunch of other
reasons um so so there's a lot of really
great things here uh to consider with
regard to What It Takes creativity and
Innovation um yesterday in the middle of
the coding I was like what if I did this
and I did I had an imagination idea
about the thing and I said and then I
ran down what it would look like like
that and then I went down another thing
you can actually Branch your code and
experiment and work out some ideas and
you can Branch it again and work it out
with another idea and come back and keep
the pieces that you want it's actually a
very creative process so anybody tells
you that programming is you know a uh
you know the whole left right brain
thing is total pseudoscience that's
never been proven anywhere um but the
the idea is is that you have an
analytical brain and you have a creative
brain the fact of the matter is they're
both creative and you know the pro the
programming process is a very creative
process um it's not just you know
analytical so so in fact I would suggest
that it's far more creative than it is
an antical because you have to imagine
ways to deconstruct the problem and that
that part of the process is 100%
creative so this is also another reason
I think that so many programmers end up
with artists I you know my wife's an
artist and strangely we have our brain
patterns on many things are similar um
the way we approach a problem the way we
break it down the way we research you
know ideas where we're curious about
everything naturally so these are all
traits of of programmers things that
people like to do in programming um
attention to detail the smallest mistake
can cook Le to un
consequences this is true I think it's
more about being assoc being making sure
that you don't just shoot things out
there right you you have a net under you
and we'll learn about being a cowboy
there are Cowboy coders out there who
would just put stuff out without really
analyzing it and don't be that right so
just be careful you do need to have
attention people can literally die uh
you Dennis last miles was talking about
this the other day that there's a bug
that literally uh if it gets hit would
take a plane out of the sky
and and I've worked on systems that were
responsible for some of the largest
financial institutions in the world and
and if you screw it up you know money
stops flowing kind of thing so you know
it people I can't I couldn't be a
surgeon like my friend because people
would die if I screw up right um he told
me a story about this his his peer
actually leaving um a clamp inside of a
guy's chest and they had to they had to
open it back up and take the clamp out
uh and I don't want to be that guy so I
it's funny because i' i' I've done the
equivalent of leave a clamping a guy
before uh coding wise uh and it's not
fun right it's not fun everybody goes
through it so you got to be you know
dedicated to detail you have to love to
learn people this is super important
that I talk about this one because
learning if you don't some people get
annoyed by the fact that things change
all the time and some people are made a
lot by that they're like oh my God
there's something new that just came out
now I'm not talking about chasing the
trends you know on YouTube or whatever
and God knows Tech is the tech YouTube
is full of trend Chasers but I'm talking
about a sincere love of challenging
yourself and finding something new to do
um and and the way that we're going to
be doing the coding today you know this
the whole terminal based go development
um really Fosters that love of learning
I one of the reasons that I'm so in love
with Unix like systems you know Linux
Unix and stuff like that is because you
just never learn it all there's always
something else to learn and as soon as
you've learned it all you've forgotten
the other stuff another reason to have
an AI right because they can they got
your back they remember what you asked
them about before so especially as you
age you know I'm here going to be my
upper 50s and you know so it is good to
have a love for Learning and a have a
way to do learning um and that we're
going to get to not taking things like
that later collaboration
communication um while coding often
requires focus on solitude to code Mage
is also a team player that collaborate
with fellow developers just watch the
stream ch's not here right now but I put
my own project out there and CH has been
interactively creating stuff with me
challenging me so coding is a the best
code is not a you know sit sequestered
in a thing and just you know hack out a
bunch of hacker man code that is not
what is a thing it's usually always a
collaborative process and if
professionally it's absolutely always a
peerreview process so you might write a
bunch of stuff on your own but you're
going to get somebody else they're going
to review you and this if you're not a
good communicator and I got to say this
because a lot of people that are
attracted to coding do not have the
skill for they don't develop the skill
or they don't think they have to develop
the skill to be a good communicator they
they don't feel like they have to be
able to show empathy that they you know
should should should you know talk to
people and add question marks to the end
of their statements so that other people
feel like they're asking for their input
instead of telling them what to do um
and you know there's a bunch of tiny
little techniques that you need to
master and we don't talk about it all in
the book um but you need to master those
to be a odor if if you cannot be uh if
you cannot communicate about your
choices and you're just saying and you
think you're better than everybody else
especially um you will not last you'll
not last you'll get a reputation as
being a know-it-all and you might be
capable but they won't want you because
you can't communicate so this is a real
important skill to develop um resiliency
and adaptability the digital Realm was
unpredictable yeah stuff is breaking all
the time people I I once add one of the
reasons I don't want to go into software
engineering uh strictly speaking in more
of an operational Pro you know a
software developer for you know
middleware developer backend developer
for an operations team is because of
this I was I I've been working as a
senior software engineer and worked on a
project for six months and they threw
the whole thing away there wasn't a
scrap of my code left they decided to
tank the project didn't want to do it
they threw it away if you are not okay
with that you know there are ways around
that so making sure that you're
participating in projects that have
longevity that you have control over
open source comes to mind for that but
the lot of times you don't have control
so I was just told this week and this is
I'm going to this a little bit of a flex
but I'm super excited about it I was
just told this week that my contribution
personally was was worth at least $3
million this year to the company and you
know they said that indirectly they said
that R team in5 was had you know created
a three by you know Improvement in
performance efficiency uh machine
learning jobs that cost a lot of money
to run in the cloud and that you know
the number the the cost before that was
above $10 million so you do the math you
know and the point of it is is that you
know you you you're going to be making a
difference in ways that you might not
see so you got to have a passion for the
craft uh because if I didn't if I was
just doing it for the
money you know I would still maybe do it
but but you also have to have resiliency
so that goes with it too right because
you know I'm like well I should get a
raise no I shouldn't get a raise but you
have to do it because you like doing it
uh even if your stuff isn't going to
make make you know do stuff later um so
BB Cod M POS in a genuine passion for
coding I don't I I I wrote this but I
don't fully agree with it um I might
actually change this
um this is I should ask my community
what they think about this this is one
of those points of introspection on my
part that I actually don't know I say
all the time that I don't like to code
and then I code for 12 hours
yesterday so but you know it says a
passion for coding I when I wrote a
passion for coding what I meant was and
I should probably change this parag a
passion for coding
because I get stuff you know I like what
I get out of it whether it's the money
or the the app or the thing that makes
me more efficient or whatever uh it's
what transform coding from skill into a
craft and from a job into call I used to
have a saying about this where I would
say um yeah in fact this is why I put
this there because I used to my my
LinkedIn used to start with uh coding is
an art and um you know I used to when I
started skill stack it was you know the
coding Arts was like joining the coding
arts and you know I don't really think
of that that way my my wife is is in the
Arts and you know I don't I don't
directly associate coding with art the
way I used to I I really feel like it
was kind of a reach now having having
been associated with the art community
um and so you know anyway uh I do enjoy
coding keep it in the book okay I'll
keep that in there I but sometimes I I
like to convince myself that that it's
that I don't like to code that I hate it
and but I like what I get but the truth
is yesterday while I was coding and I
was like listening to music and was like
playing footsies with my wife in bed
while we coded and and I was live
streaming and I was like this is great
this is amazing and you know whether it
be writing or coding I really enjoyed it
so so that that that actually was a
passion for coding so anyway age and
foundational skills um because of code
Mage is on a journey to all ages whether
you're a Young Apprentice or season
Adventure it's never too late to start
coding I've taught 65y olds how to
code and they just want to learn they've
always wanted to learn it is never too
late my friends there's probably at
least one of you watching right now uh
you started contributing to a game nice
um so the point I'm trying to make here
is it's never too late it's never too
late you know um it's you know people
there's there are videos out there on
YouTube about whether you're too old to
be a programmer and like all the really
good software Engineers like give it up
in their 30s or 40s because they burn
out and they're like do you really have
the brain to be a software engineer and
a coder in your upper pits you sound
like yes you do oh my God why would you
even say that you agist
mother you don't have to be the most
efficient software engineer or even the
most efficient developer to want to
learn how of code and to get the
benefits from it honestly and who knows
it might actually make you put off Al
Alzheimer's further because it's going
to it's better than sudoku for your
brain I'm just saying age is not a thing
okay are you ready to begin becoming a
coage is about not about perfection it's
about embracing the
journey uh if you if you're ready to
cultivate I know we're not we're not on
an hour mark no we're not I have another
um I have I started at 30 minutes after
the hour so I I'm coming at the 30
minute Mark uh life of a Cod Mage okay
are you ready to begin okay so here's
what we talk about the life of a Cod
Mage and I'm going to go through
this so Cod M this is okay so I I
thought we covered this we didn't old
man bad memory so we did so that's what
it takes it's what it takes are you
ready to do that right are you ready to
put in the time specifically are you
ready to put in at least two hours a
week two or three hours a week keeping
up your skills even after you've learned
everything um you know it it does take
several you know thousand hours to
become a true Master but you can learn
everything you need to know to become a
programmer and employed engineer uh
software developer in you know less than
a month I believe that if you dedicate
yourself to it and you specifically you
know if you're were to work like two
hours a day two or three hours a day you
could probably come up with that kind of
thing in less than but what is your life
going to look like as a code Mage so
this is this this you know this is this
is what this is about a Cod Mage lives
in an intersection of logic creativity
wielding the power of code in contous
Solutions automated Tas and and build
entire digital Realms like a crafts
person of magic their days are filled
with disc Discovery problem solving and
rentless pursuit of Mastery yes that's a
little bit of Flowery but that's what
the code Mage theme is about morning
rituals so I had to write about this the
day begins with a code M stepping out of
the sanctum a workspace DN with multiple
monitors glowing softly that's I got
three right now uh perhaps just a single
laptop and a cozy seat which I also do I
was like just out there as I told you um
a warm cup of coffee in hand and then
review the spell book often written a go
bash or JavaScript uh they study the
test in hand debugging cations designing
new algorithms collaborating with the
guild or that is literally the life the
life is is great and I got to tell you I
really love this part of the life it's
like when you wake up you know you make
your copy we have an espresso machine I
just push a button and it grinds the
beans everything it's so great and it's
like my my copy is steaming and I'm I'm
writing code and these days I'm actually
pushing start stream and so you guys are
just watching my screen over the
shoulder with me and I'm I'm IRC
chatting and I'm writing things and I'm
listening to the music and it's just
it's just glorious it's it is it's
really fun and you can do it anywhere I
still my my favorite memories of going
to New York are seriously I would go up
to New York for Christmas and I I'd say
honey can I just do the thing she goes
I'm gonna go shopping I'm like okay I
said I'm gonna go do another thing and
and I would just go find a coffee shop
and sit in the coffee shop and write
write transpiler code in Pagan or
something just because it just was so
the the atmosphere of it was so fun it's
the whole vibe the whole vibe is just I
think the vibe is the modern young
that's what young people say today the
vibe is great and particularly the vibe
in the morning the morning Vibe when you
wake up and you got your cofi and your
brain is all fresh and you just you was
working on idea I just really love it
practices of the day the book of the day
is spent moving spells writing code he
code is Cap clapter ruin combining
syntax and logic bringing ideal life Cod
man alternates between de focus and
creating complex AC this is really
important okay so you got to have Focus
having too much distraction to Coffee
Shop you know make sure you got white
noise Make sure you can put your
earplugs in make sure you can do what it
takes to get focused because when you
get into the code you're going to get
really really into it so um that's how
it goes their tools are me many the
terminal power uh terminal command line
interface with they summon combin
Version Control guilt Greenmore uh get
repository AI consultant internet tomb
of knowledge uh so again I'm just having
fun this is written for a 12 hopefully
that'll be not too silly encounters with
challenges challenges are frequent spill
my backfire causing errors to emerge B
this this is hard so the other day I got
stuck on a problem and I could not fix
it and went and had a
shower and I came back and I I knew what
the answer was so sometimes the problem
is like walking away from it so your day
is going to be filled with a lot of
problem solving and frustration but you
also have to stand up and walk away and
figure out how to break your day down so
that you can fix that up um H do you
recommend 4 early morning study sessions
or at night morning by far by far it it
really depends on whether your brain
is sharper at night or at at at in in
the evening um I very selfishly use my
best brain power for working on the
projects that I like and the projects I
want to do and for my own learning um
this is true and this is a confession of
mine I I give work my leftover brain
power which is not bad it's not bad but
I know especially as I age I know that I
have you know know only a certain number
of like really premium hours where my
brain is really really dialed in and
usually that's in the morning is
particularly after a cup of coffee and
um and I I I dedicate that time to to to
usually to things that I that I want to
do personally um sometimes however I'll
get really into a project at work and
I'm like I got to I got to use that that
good brain time for something at work um
and that's when you're going to have
your moments of Triumph right when you
break through uh a lot of times you'll
break through the next morning um I have
definitely learned to just put the
computer down uh at night so you can
actually sometimes watch this when I do
a long coding stream by the end of it
I'm making more mistakes I'm being s you
know I'm more prone to to not save a
thing I'm pausing a lot longer and yeah
I can still do the coding but it's it's
taking me a tremendous amount of time to
do the same thing that I could have done
in 10 minutes in the morning and so I
have learned I mean this this section of
the book is about understanding your
daily routine and knowing how to get
used to that and um that's a very
individual thing um I found that like
when I work out when I go for a bike
ride or something when I come back if I
take a nap or something I recover that
after that my I got a lot of oxygen in
my head and my brain is really popping a
lot of times when I go running or I'm on
the bike I actually get ideas because of
the oxygen and or when I'm doing yoga
sometimes I'll get ideas so those are
make sure you have all of those things
now that said I'm a horrible example of
this um yesterday was a good example of
me balancing uh many things while I was
cating and by the end of the day I was
like wow where did the time go because I
didn't feel drained uh you know when you
do this wrong because you forget to
drink you get so focused you don't drink
you don't eat you don't do anything else
you end up going low blood sugar your
brain stops working then you want to
fall asleep and you know so you got to
you got to be supportive of your body
and I I fail on that point all the time
so uh you know don't be me on that do be
better than me uh so yeah uh he found
that very fascinating useful as a quick
Dev environment setup solution yes
that's exactly what it is TR nice did
you see all the other stuff we're going
to come back to that we're making videos
right now so actually ch's in the chat
right now one of my collaborators on the
Bonsai project thank you very much for
your
contributions um monetizing bons yeah
why
not why not um but uh play around with
the persistence variables that I just
did by the way no CH you're fine please
make sure you go validate all the
persistence variables that I just added
particularly environment variable
shadowing all right sorry guys a little
bit of a of a Sidetrack but that's a
good example of what a day is like in
the life of a code Mage you you are
going to be collaborating with your
other Mages in your guild sometimes you
know live sometimes on a phone phone
sometimes they're going to put a PR in
they're going to be constantly you know
people are going to be asking for your
input whether it be live input or or you
know uh secondary input like you know
through a PR process or something um so
so yeah anyway so lifelong learning I've
already said this a million times if
you're not dedicated to learning and
keeping up don't do it just don't work
in Tech at all in fact I don't know I I
have worked with several people who are
like I don't want to do this anymore and
I'm like
what do you mean and they're like well I
don't want to have to learn something
new all the time and so they just stay
on the same thing until they retire I
had one guy tell me I I left when I left
IBM I had one guy tell me I'm never
leaving IBM and I like why and he's like
I just don't have it in me to like learn
something new to go so I was like What a
Sad State I I deeply love the person
that said that I I worked with them for
many years but but I it was It was kind
of disheartening to hear somebody
actually say that if you I'm talking
till the end look I'm tired I get tired
of coding too right I want to get out on
my bike and I go for months without
doing any code because I overdo it
that's more about balance but if if
you're not dedicated to lifelong
learning you know aggressive lifelong
learning um you know and and and giving
up your old ways I you know adopting new
things whether it be neim or using the
terminal or you know control the bracket
instead of control C for escape wink
wink um you know uh not doing the twitch
RC thing you don't like the twitch
RC well you can stay on YouTube but um
I'm you won't be able to participate in
my chat when when I'm just coding
because I'm not going to have chat
available on YouTube because it's too
big a risk the other day I had some
people say horrible things in YouTube
that I that I never got a chance to shut
down so that's so when I'm doing the the
non-interactive live streams like this
this is a good this is an interactive
one every time I stream like this be
you'll be safe we can chat one thing I
don't want to keep up with this front
end I'm learning that the hopping you
don't have to it's called Web they call
it Frameworks fatigue because sometimes
they come up with a new one before the
other one's even done um so yeah um so
let's see so even Reflections as the day
winds down the code Mage reflects on
progress they close the terminal a sense
of accomplishment knowing they put your
boundaries this is true um it's actually
also true that um you get really
stressed out uh
not for
YouTube uh evening Reflections okay
so uh the purpose Beyond code so I'm
actually I want to write an entire book
on this I have some ideas about this I
haven't even started it yet it's called
programming with purpose and the code
Mage doesn't write just programs they
solve problems Empower others and build
Bridges between technology and Humanity
their magic isn't limited to code but
extends to creative tools services and
experiences that make life better the
world becomes a better place around them
there's a running meme uh about in fact
it's a a regular meme topic uh in
Silicon Valley which
sazesh Valley and it's like and we're
making the world a better place through
elegant hierarchies blah blah blah right
and the point of this is that I do truly
believe that that coding can Empower you
to do other things we talked about this
a little bit but you know people through
coding have saved you know climate data
that was about to be destroyed because
it the the organization lost funding um
it could be you know whether it be
hacking it could be creating new systems
but it could be even something as boring
as what I'm doing which is just keeping
the machine learning models submitted
and running on these $25,000 gpus
effectively and efficiently for a very
large corporation that is producing
value for the world that we all
participate in and use all the time um
you know that contribution to the world
you know is is a contribution and and I
I really think that that one of the ways
that we can contribute the most to the
world is through is you know learning to
create Solutions and notice I didn't say
programming and that's because Solutions
may or may not involve programming
sometimes there are other solutions to a
problem that have nothing to do with
coding and I think it's important that
we approach the entire craft of coding
um as a way to provide Solutions I told
this story before I'm going to tell it
again I was having a beer with a guy who
was paid very a lot of money by Lowe's
as a senior consultant and he begged me
kind of drunkenly with a you know his
hand on my shoulder teach them to
provide Solutions not follow Trends
because because he was so tired of
dealing with senior technologists who
were just there for the entertainment
value of whatever the technology was and
they had lost track of the fact that
their purpose was to provide a solution
and value for the company and you know
whether you don't believe in the company
therefore you don't care about producing
value for them or you know something are
just too distracted by how cool a thing
is it's important that you remember that
you know your purpose is to code to
create Solutions and um if you want to
code for entertainment purposes and
stuff that's fine but if you're if
you're doing it on the job or I I I
think it's more valuable to you know
we're doing a we're doing everybody's
doing admin a code right now and I'm not
going to tank on it that's great if you
want to do it but it does make me really
aware of the fact of how many people
myself included can be easily distracted
by by a problem uh the entertainment
value of writing code to solve a problem
when they potentially could have been
equally entertained by producing
something of value that's more
satisfying uh with a better purpose and
I don't know what that is you can maybe
think about what that could be for you
um but you know I I wish I wish that was
more front and center so it's worth
mentioning I've been talking about it a
lot all right so we got another 25
minutes of this particular video love
prepare to code I promise you we're
going to get to the coding stuff we got
to go through this though
uh all right so we are now officially in
the prepare to code section um so this
section is i' I've spent several weeks
honing it and crafting it and pulling it
down so that it's hopefully it's just
the minimum without completely doing it
for you because I want you to learn
about it right um so learning happens in
the lab not the electrol you can't make
spells or swords in without a lab of for
so let's make one so right now what
we're going to do is going to go through
how you can code and we're going to
build you're going to build a lab and by
lab I don't mean like my one that's off
right now that's over here in the corner
I'm talking about a place for you to
write code and that place that you're
going to write code is your computer
that you're probably watching me on
right now so if you're watching me on a
phone obviously you can't do that but
you need so we're going to get into it
but you need to have a computer that's
got a keyboard and it needs to be able
to install you know a few things in
order to get to get coding um before we
get reading this I I really want you to
understand that that this is just to get
you coding the idea is is that you're
going to get coding and you're going to
productive from the terminal and you're
going to have a taste of the terminal up
front but it's not going to be you know
we're not going to make you into a
terminal Master this is focused on
getting you an experience with the
terminal that involves coding and to
become you know a good programmer but
not necessarily a terminal Master yet
that is in another book so I'm going to
put a plugin for the other book which
I've started dumping things into already
it's called terminal velocity mastering
the fastest human computer interface and
that does talk about all of those things
and the reason I have to mention this at
this time is because at this point in
the book there used to be a lot of stuff
and every beginner boas we've ever done
before spent an enormous amount of time
getting you to become a master of the
terminal before you even started writing
a line of code I mean you were writing
bash of course but you weren't writing
any actual C in terms of go and that
sort of was nice you became you know
more of a hack was more designed for
people who want to be hackers and this
is more designed for people who want to
be hackers but also just want core
programming skills um that they can then
you know move into the hacker space and
stuff like that so I need to talk about
that um I'm going to share a quick story
here in my calculus 101 class I I I told
this story before but I'm going tell it
again um so I was in a C I'm going to
I'm going to paraphrase this I was in my
calcus 101 class I was there was like
400 people in the lecture hall so and
and I was frustrated I couldn't learn a
text Tech thing and I didn't have any
hope of raising my hand and getting an
answer and I got so frustrated over the
days that happens to my first year in
college that um I started asking um you
know I asked the guy next to me I like
man it's is just so frustrated it's like
I wish there were a place where we could
like ask questions and stuff and he said
well you could always try um you could
always try the the lab the math lab I
was like what and I'm I am going to read
this part so I immediately found that I
never forget that feeling Walking In For
the First Time the warrant of the Utah
cold winter my glasses fogging everyone
having fun focusing learning chatting
getting mentored by teachers assistant
with phds and math flexing on the
struggling plees in a good way helping
them with math make it make calculus
relatable it was glorious I learned so
much in that lab the learning there was
messy and Loud because it was infectious
and effective and that's how I came by
this saying learning happens in the lab
not the lecture hall so this is messy
you're going to make a lot of mistakes
here but you should be fine um you know
as as as long as you know you you can
fix up your own computer and stuff like
that so there's nothing you're going to
do that's ever going to be like
catastrophically bad so don't be afraid
of that um here's what you're going to
need you're going to need the bash
command line and we're not I want to say
it right now go back to the the
yesterdays or the last time when I
talked about just trust me um we're not
going I'm not going to justify every one
of these decisions just just putting
this list out there on the internet is
going to get all kinds of people are
going to like wake up and in my chat
right now so I'm only going to say that
once I am not going to spend any time so
help me God help me keep with this
justifying these decisions if you want
to see these decisions Justified ask me
at another time or go read the shut the
fact up where I wrote the answers to all
those questions about why not this and
why this okay so I will we will talk
about why why we picked these things not
in comparison to everything else but we
will talk about them when we get to to
them but I just want to give the list
out there for you up front uh okay so
the bash command shell uh a GitHub
account uh a DOT files configuration a
West term terminal and we just barely
made that a thing that became a thing
within this last two weeks uh the Neo
editor which is absolutely a new thing
uh for me I've usually been a Bim guy
we'll talk about that um and go
programming language why go we'll talk
about that later uh markdown for notes
and get for saving and sharing so this
these are the core technologies that you
have to have installed and then the rest
of the prepare the prepare section of
the book goes into step by step how to
get all of this stuff set up and that is
what we're going to do with the rest of
our time today we're going to proceed
through this right now and we're going
to do the steps and I'm going to walk
you through the steps on each of the
os's so you can see how it's done um and
you can fast forward through that stuff
if you want to but it's all in
excruciating detail so that we're doing
a lot of handholding here uh you then
you'll be able to like modify it and do
it to your own after that okay so let's
move on um you don't need more than this
avoid the temptation to customize
everything for now you'll have plenty of
time to do that later as I said in the
terminal velocity section you know if
you want to install Linux and all that
stuff there's lots of things you can do
but right now we're focused on getting
to code install the bash shell all right
so the bash shell sh for Born Again shs
a versal command line interface
available on most operating systems it's
ubiquitous powerful easy to use don't
worry too much about what that means
we'll talk about it later let's just get
it so if you're on Windows you're going
to get git bash okay now what is git
bash uh git bash is just bash plus git
on Windows that's all it is it's just an
app it's not an OS or anything but it
feels like an OS and I'm going to show
you how so you type when get install D-
ID get get notice this does not have to
be uppercase because we don't have d e
in there if you know what Windgate is
you'll know about that this is going to
put into here if you have Windows you
need to launch a poers shield by typing
the wind key type of thing I'm going to
do this once for everybody and then I'm
not going to do it again all right so I
actually have Windows up in in VNC here
uh running in a different
computer and uh so that we can do this
now I've got a bunch of stuff open right
now let's go close it all out uh bunch
of stuff that I've been playing with and
setting up as you can see I've got it
all set up over here already uh a lot of
this stuff is already set up
um cancel all right so let's let's say
so the way to do this so I'm going to
press the the Windows key in this case I
think it's I think for VNC I think it's
uh I got to remember the VNC combo there
it is um so so that pulls up the search
bar
now you can get used to this keystroke
right you just push Windows key and then
you start typing and you can always type
power and it will pull up the power
shell and you push enter and that'll
pull up the power shell right now this
is really really small I'm sorry about
that um I think you can actually change
the the
um I think you can change the the uh
properties to have bigger bont if you
want to I'm going to go ahead and do
that because you guys can't see it while
I'm doing it but let's go ahead and jack
it up to
36 all right and then we'll the thing so
this is Powershell should you learn pow
shell yes but not today um we're just
getting poh because we don't have
anything else yet and so we're going to
do the install when get install and then
I'm going to go back to the to the book
information uh and we know we saw that
it was um uh bash no gitgit Das Dash is
two dashes ID uh G.G now I know it seems
like we're installing G and not bash we
are the the person you know the people
that made
git uh so this is why you're putting in
there now you'll see something else
right and and when that actually as soon
as that installs you'll be able to type
um bash D- version and you should be
able to see well actually no let's type
exit here and now let's go start bash
we'll type down here we're going to type
bash and now you see it says git bash
right so now git bash will will fire up
and we're going to go ahead and
customize git bash really quickly while
we're here um you can right click on
here you can click on options and I know
it's hard to see but you go under here
if you want to you can change the theme
I'm going to set it to groove boox theme
uh I did I did crank up the the text a
little bit I think we're what are we at
are we still at uh 36 I'm at upto mono
26 you can put whatever you want there
let's go ahead and put 36 apply okay uh
so now now we've got bash now this um
this actually is a bash that has my
configuration in it
uh already and I'm actually going to
remove that right now don't do this but
I'm going to remove this so that um you
can see what it looks like when it
doesn't have that so uh this is the this
is what it looks like when you don't
have um any configuration at all all
right mw40 that's the name of the
operating system so so this you've got
bash on Windows I mean you've got it
right so the next steps are just kind of
on top of this you know uh and this is
100% you know this is this is 100% um
you know bash and it it feels like Linux
if you know it or Unix it's not it's
100% windows but and you're in your home
directory so you PWD you can see where
you are there and you can see where this
is all in the book so let's go back to
the book and catch up with where we are
um so we got that all
installed um and we got the wind get on
there we launched it for the first time
uh update bash on Mac so if you're on a
Mac if you're on a Mac you have to get
Brew all right so this is I the hardest
part about the book here is that this I
mean this is seriously this is one of
the hardest parts about this is you're
going to have to copy and paste this um
into your um you're going to have to
copy and paste it that's all I have to
say so so if you go
to um okay okay let's let me take you
through the steps so first of all you
need to launch a terminal so on a Mac
the way you launch a thing is you push
command space if you don't know about
Spotlight yet then you need to learn
about it right so command space an A
type terminal and that'll launch the you
know the stupid terminal now mine's been
colorized and stuff yours will be
different um but that's enough right
that's enough to get you a terminal and
I've replaced terminal with westerm
which we're going to get to but for
right now this is the default built-in
terminal uh yeah so so then you can type
this in if you want uh and you know I
can almost REM remember it myself I'm
going to try to remember that because it
is the same it's actually worth
memorizing the URLs uh like this because
this is a really common way to pull down
a file off of GitHub so I'm going to go
ahead and try to remember typing it in
let see if I type it right so bash C so
what does that say that says run bash
that means you know we're going to and-
C says I'm going to send a command now
I'm going to tell you what these things
mean even though we're way way ahead of
you getting a full knowledge of all that
stuff but right now if you don't know
anything else just run it because and
know that it's going to get you brew on
your machine and then Brew is going to
get you all the other things that you
need okay so so let's go ahead and do
that so let's do bash DZ and then we're
going to put quotes around the thing and
and around that thing and we're going to
type in the command now this curl
command what that does is it goes out to
the internet and it pulls down the thing
and and downloads it to your computer um
and in this case it's actually not just
downloading it but but it's also running
it uh and if you wanted to do this as
separate steps you could in fact let me
just show you if you wanted to you could
you could take the curl command and then
just put it into a file so let's do that
uh so the
fssl and this says don't don't bother
with the output you you could actually
get rid of that if you want to see it
you really don't need all that the only
one you need you have to have is L which
says which says you know redirect if
there's a thing so let's actually try
this one you again just cut and paste if
you want but I'm doing it the long way
and how you doing uh we're making videos
so thank you for the raid um so let's do
it so htps we put this in quotes htps
col SC raw do oops. GitHub user content.
was it
IO slome Brew it doesn't have to be uh
capitalized but I don't think uh Slash
install uh slash now head I'm pretty
sure does have to be you know what let's
try it without it I've always wanted to
know I don't I think it does have to be
capitalized
install.sh all right now what is that
going to do that's going to download the
thing and let's actually tell it what we
want to call it so let's do- o and say
uh I mean we we can just keep it we can
just keep it called install that SSH
actually and if you wanted to keep the
name you can just add o here which by
the way if you want to remember it is s
it's it's like kind of like looks like
it says slow right right uh sorry if you
wanted to have that's a really common
thing that says keep the name right
otherwise you can actually rename it if
you want so we're going to run that and
that's going to download it and um you
don't know these commands yet but you
can do this you can say less
install.sh and it does not find it
because we we we did something wrong so
I push the up Arrow I'm using VI mode
but we can go to up arrow and it'll get
you back here so let's try I think
that's because I tried some things let's
try this one now let's see if that's
better yep okay so that got it and we
use less and less is our pager um and so
the Homebrew could be lowercase but the
other one this is a bash script now
eventually you're going to learn all of
this stuff and what it means but what
the reason we're looking at it is
because we want to know what's going to
run on the computer and normally you
would say hey is there anything bad
happening here right is there anything
bad that this thing is doing to my
computer and you know that at the risk
of sounding over really emphasizing on
security you really should look at all
the things you're running on your
computer instead of just downloading
them from the internet and running them
however in this case um you know there's
we we pretty much trust this this site
because this is the standard way
straight off of the main site about how
to do the install so now we can actually
run this now the way we run it is we
just do we can do bash this right we can
bash install and that will run the
program and uh you can see it's going to
ask me for my password which I am not
going to type at this time you can go
ahead and do this part uh and it will go
out to the internet and it will download
it and you'll see it there and then when
it's there you can do Brew uh I think
it's Dash is it dash dash version I
can't remember yeah Brew D- version I'll
tell you what version Brew you have now
you're ready to install things with brew
and you can do the next step so let's by
the way everything we just did is is
done in a single
line um
uh here that's what this line does so
this- C just says take this stuff by
putting this dollar around here like
this uh and the and the print that says
take the output of that command which is
why it's got so many an FSS so there's
not do got other text in there it says
take the stuff that comes out of that
and then run it as a as if it were
passed to bash that's that's the only
difference here the only difference
between doing it as two separate steps
and this is that this is just one step
so you can just copy and paste that and
have that work um so yeah somebody asked
the difference between less and more uh
more is older less is newer and my more
has been has been mapped to less uh
that's really the only difference we are
going to get it there's a section on
that later we'll talk about so um so
that's it and now you can actually Brew
install bash and you're like but I was
just using bash yes you were but the
bash you're using is really old b bash
D- version uh I W get into why the main
reason bash is really old on Mac is
because of Licensing issues they changed
the license when they went on that the
latest bash uh is actually five so how
do you get five you do this Brew install
bash and that will install bash and it
will do all the things for you okay so
uh it's actually going to get oh look at
that it's updating mine it just updated
mine and it's the same command for
anything else uh you shouldn't have to
have any special commands for that um a
lot of Mac users will already have Brew
for one reason or another um uh let's
see serious question how do you exit the
password prompt and was that in Mac uh
what's the window it was the head
character okay if you if you're on the
password prompt do contrl c which is an
interrupt so that's that's actually a
good good point I'll make sure to put
that in the book um if you can't control
C gets you interrupts sends an interrupt
which we're going to come back to
later
uh yeah copy Mode's pretty good
um so okay um so let's see what else we
got
um um all right so that we've covered
when we've covered how to get bash now
the problem with Mac unfortunately and I
hate to say this but we have these other
very very weird commands on Mac uh that
you have to do in order for it to see
your shell and um what it's doing is
it's adding the newer Homebrew bash to
your shell so in this particular case
you're just going to have to run this
and and copy and paste it or type it in
and I'm not going to do it right now I'm
going to skip past it what that will do
is that when you log in you'll make your
default shell available and it will use
the new updated bash um I have seriously
debated about whether to have uh the
bash install steps at all
in this and I actually after having just
talked about it I've decided to delete
it so if you don't want to do this you
can just skip it if you want to skip the
Brew install bash you can in fact if you
want to St skip the entire section about
setting bash up on a Mac you can because
bash version 3 is enough it bash version
3 is enough for you to do you know
coding sorts of things uh I mean I think
it should be
um I I don't know if it's going to
affect your dot files though so we'll
we'll check that out and make sure but
there's a good chance you're not going
to need to do the the The Bash install
although most of you are probably going
to want to do it anyway so anyway um
we're coming up on the hour mark we have
about 10 minutes left so let's just talk
about Linux and then we'll talk about
GitHub and then you can go off and make
your own accounts while we're taking a
break so Linux already has bash bash is
a default shell for most uh Linux and
Unix system Linux systems and um
therefore you don't need to do any
upgrades to it at all it's already there
if you for some reason have Linux which
normally you'd have to install um then
that's where we are all right so let's
move on to GitHub GitHub is one of the
most powerful platforms from
collaboration coding and sharing uh
create a Gib account is essential for
developer students and anyone looking to
participate in open source even if you
don't like Gib or Microsoft doesn't
matter you have to have it here's a
guide for how you can create account why
it matters uh why I get of account uh
Version Control guub is built on git
distributed Version Control System made
by the Lin wals the inventor of Linux
who helps track your changes in code
collaborate with others and maintain
history of your work uh collaboration
GitHub enables teams and communities to
work together on projects share ideas
code feedback the chit and I were just
talking about it actually in the chat
portfolio building you I had I had a
senior Executive Vice President and
after I Mentor her son talk to me about
how they use this very stealthy highly
expensive service to identify people to
be hired from their GitHub profile uh
whether they contribute how they
contribute what their code is and that's
a true story um and and if I mean I wish
I could tell you more about the company
uh obviously I can that would be
seriously doxing her um and anyway so I
know for a fact that getto profiles uh
are evaluated uh by Ai and by other
tools to make qualified suggestions to
people that are hiring uh it doesn't
take much searching on the internet to
find stories about people who have been
offered jobs straight up just from their
GI up profiles uh have I ever been
offered a job from my getup profile no
probably because it's full of like
beginner Noob stuff that I'm helping but
you know it it is you know it's a thing
so profiles are a thing uh I think it's
more important for you to have a profile
in GitHub than LinkedIn and we'll get
into that eventually accessing your open
source projects millions of Open Source
projects are on there this is where the
source code generally is if you want to
go just read the source Luke um you know
you can go study the source with you're
trying this has helped me out I I I I
downloaded the the the API for
kubernetes which is a big Enterprise
Cloud application and I was able to look
through the source code and get answers
to things that were not documented
because I was able to read The Code by
the way that code is in go so just
learning the stuff you're going to learn
in this book is going to make you a
better employee with regard to reading
go because every single major Cloud
dative application was written go so
being able to read it and understand it
is super important um so integration
access to the open source projects so
GitHub is is strongly integrated into
all sorts of other things GitHub has its
own University uh that they created
because they couldn't get people to
learn the stuff that you were going to
learn in the book and elsewhere um
because they couldn't get people to do
it and so they can't sell the product if
they don't have people that can use this
thing so Gib has the most powerful API
of any of the apis I've seen it has the
most powerful command line tool which I
need to put a thing in there I I forgot
about that the GI up command line tool
that we're going to install is by far
the most the most powerful uh command
line integration with any Source
management tool I've ever seen so much
so that gitlab has stolen it and forgot
to change some of the GitHub references
in the source code I understand somebody
just told me that two days ago because
they're so they're so far behind I mean
it's just amazing and you're going to
see how it's amazing um so how do you go
create a GitHub account go to GitHub go
to the website I mean I don't have to
tell you this you guys know how to do
this right sign up click on the sign up
button put in your thing pick a username
that's got lower cases and no spaces
this is one of the biggest annoyances I
have I if I look you do you if you want
to do that fine there a lot of people
that disagree but I think you should
keep short memorable sustainable um you
know user IDs that people can remember
so because they're going to have they're
it's your brand they're going to need to
be able to go find you again and they're
not going to remember how to type you
into the URL spend some time thinking of
a really interesting but short username
and use it for the rest of your life
make your emails that maybe make a
domain that I mean artex Rob took me
some time to figure that one out but but
you know I think you should I think you
should really spend some time on this
you know Minecraft hates creeper 277 is
like no it's
no so verify your email we already
talked about you need to have an email
account this is why choose a plan you
can do the free plan uh for now I I
actually pay because I like private um
private repos that have geub websites
but I probably also I just like
supporting GitHub honestly honestly I
like supporting them even though
Microsoft behind them um is your name of
bad name I mean I think so it just is it
memorable I I would I would shoot for
name that's that personally I would
shoot for a name that's under 10
characters that's just me but
everybody's got different choices on
this uh for some of the repos you can go
follow a few repos um you can get a list
of the repos that I follow uh AR ofix
Rob on gi.com ARX Rob um you can you
know you go have a have a a peek at that
uh why GitHub now uh creating GitHub
account is just a task it's an invit
isn't just a task it's an invitation to
join a global Community developers I
sound like I'm Shilling for Microsoft
right here I'm not I'm not I'm really
not I'm Shilling for you this is going
to help you be better in in in a million
different ways uh and so whether you're
learning a code magical managing
personal projects contributing open
source taking notes get up provides the
tools of visibility for your skills to
connect with others start your journey
today God Rob I sound I sound like the
Sham wow guy there don't I uh and become
part of the development sometimes I read
my my own stuff I'm like did I write
that yeah okay so um install git and
GitHub tool so we're going to do this
next we're going to take a break by the
way that that is the end of this video
so this is this has been um holiday
Boost number two and we've gotten to the
point where we're installing the GitHub
tool and uh we're going to do two more
videos today so we probably will get all
the way through the prepare section if
everything goes well um so take a coffee
break I'm going to take a break and join
me for the next video